Robert Bogdan Disability Collection
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Robert Bogdan Disability Collection
1820-2000
1900-1940
Ms Coll 61
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
14
(large ring binders)
The collection contains real photo postcards, commercial postcards, photographs, pamphlets and ephemera related to people with disabilities, mostly from the United States, collected by Professor Robert Bogdan, a pioneer in the teaching of disability studies.
Bogdan, Robert
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is available for research.
Scope and Contents
There are over 3,500 items in the collection, covering mainly the period from approximately 1870, when photographic images became widely available, through the 1970s, when the disability rights movement became an important force for social change. The items have been arranged by Dr. Bogdan in 14 large three-ring binders organized by topics. Their format varies but the great majority of the materials are postcards, and most of those are "real photo postcards." Real photo postcards, as opposed to commercial photo postcards, were taken by individuals and developed on postcard stock rather than on photo paper. These postcards show people with a range of disabilities participating in regular life, pictures that might be found in family albums. The people are photographed as family members, friends and loved ones, not as clinical types. Other photo formats include cartes de visite, cabinet cards, as well as larger photographs, and snapshots. These are complemented by pamphlets and other printed materials. There are over one hundred pieces related to begging, primarily ephemera used by people with disabilities to solicit money. In addition, there are hundreds of items associated with organizations, both charities assisting people with disabilities, and other institutions where people with disabilities were confined. Most of the materials are from the United States, but some are from other countries.
Arrangement
The numbering and titles of the volumes and the order of the images was determined by Professor Bogdan.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Bogdan is Professor Emeritus of Social Science and Education at Syracuse University. He compiled an archive guided by the ideas of the field of Disability Studies, an approach that focuses on "disability" as a social, cultural, and political phenomenon. An early pioneer in that field, Bogdan has taught courses related to it since 1971. He started collecting disability ephemera in the early 1980s in order to advance his research and writing. As Bogdan began collecting he realized that although there were archives and collections related to specific aspects of disability and particular disability-related organizations, none took a broad Disability Studies approach.
Custodial History
The materials were collected by Professor Robert Bogdan. They were purchased by the Historical Library in 2018.
Amputees; Beggars; Blindness; Cerebral palsy; Children with disabilities; Conjoined twins; Crutches; Deafness; Disabled veterans; Dwarfs (Persons); Epileptics; Freak shows; Guide dogs; Mental illness; Mental retardation; People with mental disabilities -- Care; Muscular dystrophy; Orthopedic apparatus; People with disabilities; People with disabilities -- Portraits; People with disabilities -- Services for; People with disabilities and the performing arts; Poliomyelitis; Prosthesis; Psychiatric hospitals; Reconstruction (1914-1939); Medicine -- Religious aspects; Sociology of disability; Tuberculosis -- Hospitals; Tuberculosis in children -- Prevention; Wheelchairs; World War, 1914-1918; Blind -- Institutional care; Deaf -- Institutional care; Orphanages; Quacks and quackery; Charities, Medical -- United States; Commemorative postage stamps; Pamphlets; Photographic postcards; Postcards; Portrait photographs; Ephemera; Photographs; Cartes-de-visite (card photographs)
- Book 1: Wheelchairs, ca. 1900-1960s (Volume 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Binder containing primarily "real photo post cards" of individuals in a wheelchair, either alone, with their family, or in a group. Real photo postcards were created from photos taken by individuals and developed on postcard stock. They date from 1900 to about 1930. Also included toward the back are some advertisements for wheelchairs in postcard format, some cartes de visite, and some later snapshots.
- Book 2: People (General), ca. 1900-1956 (Volume 2)
  This binder contains photos of people with disabilities that might be found in family albums. Most of the items are real photo postcards.
- Book 3: Veterans; Charity, ca. 1907-1989 (Volume 3)
  The first part of this binder is on disabled veterans, especially from World War I, and the rehabilitation of veterans. The second part of the binder contains materials on charities for children with physical disabilities, poliomyelitis, cerebral palsy, muscular dystrophy, blindness and guide dogs, deafness, and sickle cell anemia (1 item). The volume contains real photo postcards, printed postcards, photographs, stamps issued by charities, and some pamphlets and other ephemera.
- Book 4: Begging; Town Characters; Performers; Exhibits, 1880s-1950s (Volume 4)
  The section on "Begging" has postcards or ephemera that disabled people handed out to ask for charity.
  The section on "Town Characters" contains mostly printed postcards of unusual people including dwarfs and bearded hermits.
  "Performances" includes images of disabled people as musical performers, artists, or athletes. There are several cards about dwarfs in performances.
  "Exhibits" includes people who were exhibited at side shows or elsewhere. Some were disabled or dwarfs; others were of unusual ethnicities. Includes the Dionne quintuplets and Tom Thumb.
  Binder contains real photo postcards, printed postcards, cartes de visite, and other ephemera.
- Book 5: Merchants; Advertising; Healers; Royalty, ca. 1900-1990s (Volume 5)
  "Merchants" contains (1) images of people with disabilities or dwarfs working in stores or offering products and services; and (2) merchants offering artificial limbs, wheelchairs, hearing aids, etc.
  "Healers" includes various evangelists such as Aimee Semple McPherson and Oral Roberts, miracle cures, and medical/quack healers. Among them are John Till, "Plaster Healer," and Mahlon W. Locke and his clinic.
  "Royalty" includes images of European royalty such as Princess Alexandrine of Prussia/Germany who had Down's Syndrome, Prince John Charles Francis Windsor of Kent (1905-1919) who was said to have had epilepsy, King George VI (1895-1952) who stammered, and several others.
- Book 6: Institutions: Insane, Feeble minded, Epileptic, Deaf, Blind, ca. 1900-1930. (Volume 6)
  Section 1 includes images, mostly printed postcards, of mental institutions, especially state hospitals. Section 2 has postcards of state homes for the "feeble minded." Section 3 has images of homes or hospitals for epileptics. Section 4 has postcards of schools for the blind and deaf.
- Book 7: Institutions: Physically Disabled, Orphanages, 1900-1950s (Volume 7)
  Section 1 contains photos and postcards of rehabilitation and hospitals for crippled children, among them Shriners Hospitals. Section 2 contains images of orphanages and of Father Flanagan's Boys Home. The collection also includes some Boys Town stamps.
- Book 8: Institutions: County Homes, Sanatoriums, Other, ca. 1900-1974 (Volume 8)
  "County Homes includes homes for the elderly and other group homes and hospitals. "Sanatoriums" includes photographs and postcards of institutions to treat tuberculosis. One large section consists of photographs by Frank N. Ruslander of the J. N. Adam Memorial Hospital, Perrysbury, N.Y., some showing the hospital's preventorium -- children outdoors wearing minimal clothing as a means of preventing tuberculosis. There are also scenes from hospitals and groups of nurses. In "Other" there are postcard views of Gheel, more hospitals and patients, and missions to lepers in Madagascar and elsewhere. The volume ends with a series of larger photographs taken by Norman Burdick for the State Hospital for Criminal Insane, Dannemora, New York, ca. 1919.
- Book 9: Comic [postcards], 1st Day Covers, Other, ca. 1900-1997 (Volume 9)
  Comic postcards in this volume caricature people with physical disabilities or mental illness, or in some cases people pretending to have a disability in order to solicit money. The second section contains miscellaneous photographs and postcards on people with disabilities, including "invalid" radio operators, and more material on Franklin Roosevelt and polio (see Book 3). The third section contains first day covers of U.S. postage stamps related to people with disabilities or to charitable organizations aiding the disabled.
- Book 10: Cabinet Photos, 1870s-1920s (Volume 10)
  The cabinet card format was used by professional photographers for portraiture from the 1870s to the 1920s. It is larger than the similar carte de visite. These photographs are of people with a variety of physical disabilities. The last three cabinet cards in this volume -- Alfred Pilgrim, Uncle Frank Jeffrey's family, and an unnamed African American -- were purchased by the Historical Library in 2018 and added.
- Book 11: Larger Format Photographs, 1880s-1973 (Volume 11)
  Photographs up to 8 x 10 on previously noted topics. There are also some publicity photographs from popular motion pictures. The volume ends with twelve stereoscopic photographs.
- Book 12: Pamphlets, 1820s-1997 (Volume 12)
  Pamphlets, mostly published by organizations helping the disabled. There are also some biographical accounts of individuals. The earliest is Happy Poverty: An Authentic History of Blind Ellen published in the 1820s by the American Tract Society.
- Book 13: Pamphlets, 1863-ca. 1997 (Volume 13)
  Materials are similar to those in the previous volume. The 1863 item is a pamphlet on Tom Thumb. The ca. 1997 item is a poster on the Disability Project. Of note is a pamphlet, Glimpses of the Pan-American Exposition (1901) in the shape of a buffalo head.
- Book 14: Snapshots, 1940s-1978 (Volume 14)
  Informal photographs of people with disabilities and their families or institutions.